{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This route's eastern half was used by people who split off onto the Mormon or Bozeman paths\ninstead of finishing this route. This route existed for twenty-five years before it became suitable\nfor wagon usage as far as Fort Hall. At the end of its use, it went all the way to the Willamette\nValley. For 10 points, name this iconic route used by settlers to the Pacific Northwest.",
      "answer": "Oregon Trail"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2014, a Senate candidate from this state was criticized for posting graphic X-rays on his\nwebsite; that second cousin of Barack Obama, Milton Wolf, failed to win the Republican\nnomination here. This state is where independent Greg Orman sought to unseat the then incumbent Pat\nRoberts. For 10 points, name this state governed by Laura Kelly from Topeka.",
      "answer": "Kansas"
    },
    {
      "question": "Shoshone [sho-sho-nay] Falls and Twin Falls lie on this river, whose largest tributary is the Salmon\nRiver. In 1974, Evel Knievel’s Skycycle X-2 nearly jumped a canyon of this tributary of the Columbia\nRiver. For ten points, name this river that flows through Hells Canyon after receiving the Boise River\nnear the border of Oregon and Idaho.",
      "answer": [
        "Snake River",
        "Snake"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Yaghan people are native to this island chain. Its largest city of Ushuaia [oosh-WHY-uh] was\nestablished as a penal colony and is served by the End of the World Train. The Drake Passage lies south\nof this island chain, and far fewer ships rounded its Cape Horn after the opening of the Panama Canal.\nFor ten points, name this archipelago shared between Chile and Argentina on the southern tip of South\nAmerica, whose Spanish name translates as “land of fire.”",
      "answer": "Tierra del Fuego"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) What island off the coast of Italy is home to Cosa Nostra, a notorious crime syndicate\noften called “the Mafia?”",
      "answer": "Sicily"
    },
    {
      "question": "A poem about this river notes that “Wushan’s clouds and rain” will be held back by “walls of\nstone.” Those walls predicted a dam, completed in 2012, that now blocks silt from traveling downstream,\npotentially weakening Shanghai on its mouth. The Three Gorges Dam was built on, for ten points, what\nlongest river in Asia?",
      "answer": [
        "Yangtze River",
        "Yangtze"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) What American state is home to the world’s largest coin mint and, with Washington,\nlegalized marijuana growing in 2012?",
      "answer": "Colorado"
    },
    {
      "question": "After winning the Battle of Gonzales, this region entered a war with its southern neighbor. One\nPresident of this region, Mirabeau Lamar, created the almost worthless “redback” to combat debt. This\nregion used the Lone Star flag and lost the Battle of the Alamo. For ten points, name this region where\nStephen Austin and Sam Houston lived, now a large American state.",
      "answer": [
        "Texas",
        "Republic of Texas"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "To extend its shoreline, this city built the Palm Jumeirah, just south of a set of hundreds of small\nartificial islands in the shape of the world. A three-lobed skyscraper in this city uses spiralling setbacks\nalong its 160 floors. For ten points, name this most populous city in the United Arab Emirates, where oil\nrevenue has spurred urban construction like the Burj Khalifa.",
      "answer": "Dubai"
    },
    {
      "question": "This body of water’s southern shore was home to the Achaemenid province of Hyrcania. Astrakhan\nlies on a river delta that empties into this body of water, where demand for caviar has caused the\nBeluga sturgeon to be overfished. The world’s first offshore oil platform was built in this sea near Baku,\nAzerbaijan. For ten points, name this salty inland sea, considered the largest lake in the world.",
      "answer": [
        "Caspian Sea",
        "Caspian"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "On May 19th, 2014, this river flowed into the Sea of Cortez for the first time in twenty years. A\nmisdug irrigation canal that diverted water from this river led to the creation of the Salton Sea. The Glen\nCanyon Dam is one of 15 dams on this river, providing irrigation for much of the Southwest and creating\nreservoirs like Lake Powell. For ten points, name this river that flows through the Grand Canyon.",
      "answer": [
        "Colorado River",
        "Colorado"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Chicago’s Marina Towers provides 19 stories of this feature, which is often required in residential\nareas at a ratio of 1 unit per residence. These features may contribute to climate change by replacing\ngreen areas with paved asphalt. The Americans With Disabilities Act requires a certain percentage of\nthese places to be reserved for handicap-accessible use. For ten points, name this urban feature found\noutside stores and along curbs, where cars are left when not in use.",
      "answer": [
        "parking spaces",
        "parking lots"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "For many years, Ohio Congressman Ralph Regula blocked attempts to rename this landmark, which\nis normally climbed by the West Buttress Route. Gold prospector William Dickey coined a name for this\npeak; in 2015, that name was officially replaced by its local Athabascan name, translating to “the high\none.” For ten points, name this highest peak in North America, an Alaska mountain that was previously\nnamed Mount McKinley.",
      "answer": "Denali"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Fuller Syndicate invested in these systems as part of the Gould system. The Gadsden Purchase\nwas completed to obtain good land for one these systems. Acts passed in 1862 and 1863 created land\ngrants and set a uniform gauge for these systems, one of which was finished at Promontory, Utah with a\ngolden spike. The Union Pacific and Central Pacific collaborated on the first of, for ten points, what 19th\ncentury construction projects that allowed quick transport across the U.S.?",
      "answer": "transcontinental railroad"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) What largest island in the North Atlantic had its capital officially renamed from Godthab to Nuuk (pr. noo-ook)?",
      "answer": "Greenland"
    },
    {
      "question": "The “Buena Vista Tract” in this city features streets named for Mexican War generals. To make room\nfor this city’s Civic Arena, many blocks of its African-American Hill District were demolished. This city’s\nPoint State Park preserves the site of a fort that was targeted by General Braddock in the French and\nIndian War. Fort Duquesne [do-kane] was built at the confluence of the Monogahela and Allegheny Rivers\nin what is now, for ten points, what city in western Pennsylvania?",
      "answer": "Pittsburgh"
    },
    {
      "question": "This body of water names Joshua Barney’s flotilla of barges that fought in the Battle of Bladensburg.\nFor almost a century until the 1950s, pirates fought a ban on dredging mollusks in this bay in the “Oyster\nWars.” The Comte de Grasse defeated the British in a 1781 battle at the mouth of this bay, which is\nfed by the York and Susquehanna Rivers and traversed by a bridge-tunnel that connects the Hampton\nRoads area to the Delmarva Peninsula. For ten points, name this large bay that is shared by Virginia and\nMaryland, the largest estuary in the United States.",
      "answer": [
        "Chesapeake Bay",
        "Chesapeake"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. In 1980, Reinhold Messner became the first person to perform this action\nsolo. In 1975, Junko Tabei became the first woman to perform this action, which often involves traversing\nthe Khumbu Icefall. After performing this action in 1988, Jean-Marc Boivin paraglided for his descent\ndown to Camp 2. In 1953, Tenzing Norgay and Sir Edmund Hillary became the first people to accomplish,\nfor ten points, what feat of conquering the tallest peak in the Himalayas?",
      "answer": [
        "climbing Mount Everest",
        "climb Everest",
        "summiting Mount Everest",
        "reaching the top of Mount Everest"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1893, this country’s eastern border was set at a line drawn by Mortimer Durand that passes\nthrough the Spin Ghar mountains. The Amu Darya partially forms this country’s border with Tajikistan.\nA pair of sandstone Buddhas in this country’s Bamiyan Valley were dynamited in 2001 by its ruling\nTaliban, and the Khyber Pass is the main border crossing between this country and Pakistan. For ten\npoints, name this mountainous central Asian country whose capital is Kabul.",
      "answer": [
        "Islamic Republic of Afghanistan",
        "Afghanistan"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This state claims Machias Seal Island, and the oldest national park east of the Mississippi is on\nits Mount Desert Island. Its Baxter State Park is home to Mount Kathadin, and it is home to Acadia\nNational Park. Part of its northern border was set at the St. John’s River by the Webster-Ashburton\nTreaty, which settled the Aroostook War. The Appalachian Trail’s northern end is in, for ten points, what\nU.S. state that was originally part of Massachusetts in the north of New England?",
      "answer": "Maine"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This state's Jackson County is where the Garden of Eden was located in Mormon belief. This\nstate was added to the U.S. as a slave state in exchange for Maine coming in as a free state, in its\nnamesake \"compromise.\" For 10 points, name this state that shares its name with the longest\nriver in the USA, which meets the Mississippi River here near the Gateway Arch in St. Louis.",
        "answer": "Missouri"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Missouri city of Independence was the start of what route, which settlers took to\nreach the Willamette Valley?",
        "answer": "Oregon Trail"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Argun and Ussuri rivers demarcate part of the border between these two countries. These\ntwo countries established their border in 1689 with the Treaty of Nerchinsk, which ended a brief\nconflict in the Amur River region. These two countries share a border in between Mongolia and\nKazakhstan. For 10 points, name these two geographically largest countries in Asia.",
        "answer": "Russia and China"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Soviet leader's \"Secret Speech\" denouncing Stalinism was the turning point in the\nSino-Soviet split of the 1950s?",
        "answer": [
          "Nikita Khrushchev",
          "Khrushchev",
          "Nikita Sergeyevich Khrushchev"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city built the luxurious Segovia Bridge over the unimpressive Manzanares (pr. mon-zuhNAH-race) River. This home of the Queen Sofia Museum became capital in 1560, replacing\nToledo. The palace El Escorial (pr. ess-core-ee-AHL) is found just outside this city, which is the\nhome of the Prado art museum. For 10 points, name this capital of Spain.",
        "answer": "Madrid"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Las Ventas site in Madrid is used for what activity, the subject of Ernest\nHemingway's Death in the Afternoon?",
        "answer": [
          "bullfighting",
          "bullfight"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Nobukazu Kuriki lost 9 fingers at this location in 2012, and a 1996 disaster here that killed Scott\nFischer was chronicled in Jon Krakauer’s Into Thin Air. No one summited this peak in 2015 after an April\nearthquake killed 19 people at its base camp and Nepal closed it for the season. The guide Tenzing Norgay\nand Sir Edmund Hillary were the first to climb, for ten points, what tallest mountain in the world?",
        "answer": [
          "Mount Everest",
          "Everest",
          "Sagarmatha",
          "Chomolungma"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Tenzing Norgay was a member of what Nepalese ethnic group, famous for guiding Himalayan\nmountain climbers?",
        "answer": "Sherpa"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "France briefly held Fort Caroline in what is now this state’s Timucuan Preserve. After the Seven\nYears’ War, this region was split into east and west sections at the Apalachicola River. The Adams-Onis\nTreaty ceded this region to the United States, which had been fighting the Seminoles in this territory\nand nearby Georgia. For ten points, name this once-Spanish territory, now a U.S. state with capital\nTallahassee.",
        "answer": [
          "Florida Territory",
          "Florida",
          "Spanish Florida"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Spanish explorer searched for the Fountain of Youth in Florida in 1513.",
        "answer": [
          "Juan Ponce de Leon",
          "Leon",
          "Ponce de Leon"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country owns, but is not allowed to navigate, the western wetlands surrounding Lago Merin at\nthe delta of the Yaguaron River. Its western border is a river named for this country; that river combines\nwith the Parana River to form the Rio de la Plata. For ten points, name this country southwest of Brazil\nwhose capital is Montevideo.",
        "answer": "Uruguay"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This country across the Uruguay River from Uruguay shares an agricultural region called the\nPampas with Uruguay, and also shares Patagonia with Chile.",
        "answer": "Argentina"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The neighborhood of Marble Hill was separated from this island by the construction of a canal in\n1895. Its original source of fresh water, Collect Pond, was landfilled and became the site of the Five Points\nslum. This island’s neighborhood of Battery Park City was built from land excavated from a Minoru\nYamasaki-designed skyscraper project, and a low-lying area in the north of this island became a center\nof African-American culture. For ten points, what island in New York City is home to Harlem and the\nWorld Trade Center?",
        "answer": "Manhattan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Battery Park City was built on the banks of what river, which separates Manhattan from New\nJersey?",
        "answer": [
          "Hudson River",
          "Hudson"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Tomas Cloma established the Free Territory of Freedomland in this body of water. The “nine-dotted\nline” designates one country’s territorial claims in this body of water. Several countries dispute the\npotential oil reserves of this body of water’s Paracel and Spratly Islands. For ten points, name this body\nof water that borders the Philippines, Vietnam, and a large Asian country.",
        "answer": [
          "South China Sea",
          "South China"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This island, part of the smallest Chinese province, is in the South China Sea. China claims the\nSpratly Islands as part of this island province.",
        "answer": "Hainan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The largest city in this country is home to the Ipiranga Monument, where its founder proclaimed\nits independence in 1822. Oscar Niemeyer planned a new capital city for this country in 1956, to replace\na southern city on Guanabara Bay that hosted the 2016 Summer Olympics. For ten points, name this\nSouth American country, whose city of Sao Paulo is the largest in the Americas and whose capital was\nonce Rio de Janeiro.",
        "answer": "Brazil"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This planned city in central Brazil replaced Rio de Janeiro as capital in 1960.",
        "answer": "Brasilia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city’s patron saint supposedly picked up his head and walked for ten kilometers after being\nmartyred. That saint was Saint Denis [son deh-NEE], for whom this city’s district of Montmartre is\nnamed. One university in this city was built in 1253 in its Latin Quarter, and the Pont Neuf in this city\nwas built in the 16th century by Henry III. The Tuileries Palace was located in, for ten points, what city,\nwhich also contains the Sorbonne and the Louvre?",
        "answer": "Paris"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1123, Maurice de Sully began construction of this Parisian cathedral on the Ile de la Cite [eel\nde la see-tay], which is famous for its flying buttresses.",
        "answer": [
          "Notre Dame de Paris",
          "Notre Dame"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A man in this region claimed to be the Mahdi, the redeemer in Islam, and fought the Battle of\nOmdurman against the British. This region was the site of a coup by Omar al-Bashir. Chinese Gordon\ndied in this region while defending a city near the confluence of the Blue and White Nile. For ten points,\nname this geographic region of Africa south of Egypt, home to a country whose southern portion gained\nindependence in 2011, and whose remaining portion has its capital at Khartoum.",
        "answer": "the Sudan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Since 2003, this western sub-region of Sudan has been the site of brutal violence, as Janjaweed\nmilitia have supported Omar al-Bashir’s forces.",
        "answer": "Darfur"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The upper portion of this waterway was known as the Grand River until 1921. The Alamo Canal, built\nto irrigate the Imperial Valley with this river’s water, failed in 1905, creating the Salton Sea. Construction\nof the Glen Canyon Dam created Lake Powell on this river, which often failed to flow all the way to the\nGulf of California. For ten points, name this river in the western United States that flows through the\nGrand Canyon.",
        "answer": [
          "Colorado River",
          "Colorado"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This structure, once called Boulder Dam, was built on the Colorado River during the Great\nDepression. Lake Mead filled behind this structure, which is named for a former President.",
        "answer": [
          "Hoover Dam",
          "Hoover"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "ITALIAN CITIES",
      "prompt": "Which Italian city...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Is home to the Colosseum?",
          "answer": "Rome"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the supposed site of Galileo’s experiment dropping weights off the Leaning Tower?",
          "answer": "Pisa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is situated on over one hundred islands, separated by canals?",
          "answer": "Venice"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the capital of Tuscany and the birthplace of the Renaissance?",
          "answer": "Florence"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is home to La Scala Opera House and was ruled by the Visconti family?",
          "answer": "Milan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the birthplace of Christopher Columbus?",
          "answer": "Genoa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the “fair” setting of Shakespeare’s Romeo and Juliet?",
          "answer": "Verona"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is home to many of Palladio’s villas and an 800-year old university where Galileo taught math?",
          "answer": "Padua"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "BODIES OF WATER",
      "prompt": "What body of water is or was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Almost crossed by the Titanic?",
          "answer": [
            "Atlantic Ocean",
            "Atlantic"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Known as “nostrum marum” by the Romans, and is between Europe and Africa?",
          "answer": [
            "Mediterranean Sea",
            "Mediterranean"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The historic border between France and Germany?",
          "answer": [
            "Rhine River",
            "Rhine"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Between Spain and Morocco, and was the mythical location of the pillars of Heracles?",
          "answer": [
            "Strait of Gibraltar",
            "Gibraltar"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Connected to the Mediterranean by the Strait of Otranto, and dominated by Venice?",
          "answer": [
            "Adriatic Sea",
            "Adriatic"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Once terrorized by the Victual Brothers, and connected to the North Sea by the Kiel Canal?",
          "answer": [
            "Baltic Sea",
            "Baltic"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The target of the Gallipoli campaign?",
          "answer": "the Dardanelles"
        },
        {
          "question": "Where the USS Maddox was attacked by three North Vietnamese gunboats?",
          "answer": [
            "Gulf of Tonkin",
            "Tonkin"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "ENGLISH CITIES",
      "prompt": "Which English city...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Is its capital, led by Mayor Boris Johnson?",
          "answer": "London"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is home to the oldest English-speaking university, a rival of Cambridge?",
          "answer": "Oxford"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the Merseyside port where the Beatles formed?",
          "answer": "Liverpool"
        },
        {
          "question": "Has a shrine to Archbishop Thomas Becket to which pilgrims traveled in a work by Chaucer?",
          "answer": "Canterbury"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the setting of the Robin Hood legend, as its sheriff tried to capture Robin Hood?",
          "answer": "Nottingham"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the launching city for the Titanic and for the Pilgrim-carrying Mayflower?",
          "answer": "Southampton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lost its six-hundred-year old cathedral to a German air raid in November 1940?",
          "answer": "Coventry"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the setting for The Condition of the Working Class in England by Engels?",
          "answer": "Manchester"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "AUSTRALIA",
      "prompt": "In Australia, what is...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The largest city, home to a famous opera house designed by Jorn Utzon?",
          "answer": "Sydney"
        },
        {
          "question": "The capital, grown by Sir Robert Menzies?",
          "answer": "Canberra"
        },
        {
          "question": "The city targeted by Japanese air strikes in World War II and named for the English author of The\nOrigin of Species?",
          "answer": [
            "Darwin",
            "Charles Darwin",
            "Port Darwin"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The name of the vast, arid region of largely unsettled inland Australia?",
          "answer": "Outback"
        },
        {
          "question": "The island state once known as Van Diemen’s Land?",
          "answer": "Tasmania"
        },
        {
          "question": "The largest state and former site of the Swan River Colony?",
          "answer": "Western Australia"
        },
        {
          "question": "The city that annually hosts the Australian Open of tennis and hosted the 1956 Summer Olympics?",
          "answer": "Melbourne"
        },
        {
          "question": "The bay where James Cook first landed the Endeavour in Australia?",
          "answer": [
            "Botany Bay",
            "Botany"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "EUROPEAN RIVERS",
      "prompt": "Which European river...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Saw Dutch ships sail up it to attack London?",
          "answer": [
            "River Thames",
            "Thames"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Had Joan of Arc’s ashes thrown into it in Rouen, and passes through Paris?",
          "answer": [
            "River Seine",
            "Seine"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Flows through four European capitals into the Black Sea and was once home to the island of Ada\nKaleh?",
          "answer": [
            "Danube River",
            "Danube"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was Rome founded on in the eighth century BC?",
          "answer": [
            "Tiber River",
            "Tiber"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was crossed by Julius Caesar to start a civil war against Pompey the Great?",
          "answer": [
            "Rubicon River",
            "Rubicon"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the site of a World War I British offensive paired with Verdun?",
          "answer": [
            "Somme River",
            "Somme"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Names a Soviet offensive with the Oder River that targeted Poland and flows through Warsaw?",
          "answer": [
            "Vistula River",
            "Vistula"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Names a group of Cossacks and a city named Rostov on the Sea of Azov?",
          "answer": [
            "Don River",
            "Don"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country's dictator Hilarión Daza sparked a war by instituting a saltpeter tax,\nleading to this country losing its coastline in the Treaty of Ancón. Both Butch Cassidy and\nChe Guevara were killed in this country, which lost southeastern territory to Paraguay in\nthe (20 pts) ",
        "Chaco War. This country, the site of the Potosí silver mine, is now led by (10 pts) ",
        "coca\nenthusiast Evo Morales. For 10 points, identify this South American country named for the\ncontinent's \"liberator.\""
      ],
      "answer": "Bolivia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) TANAPA manages this mountain’s Lemosho trail. First summited by Hans Meyer, it\nconsists three connected cones: Shira, Mawenzi, and one renamed by (20 pts) ",
        "Julius Nyerere\nto celebrate his nation’s independence, Kibo. This mountain’s Arrow Glacier doesn’t exist\nanymore, and all the ice on (10 pts) ",
        "its Uhuru Peak is expected to disappear by 2060. For ten points,\nwhat dormant, snow-capped volcano in Tanzania is the highest point in Africa?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Mount Kilimanjaro",
        "Kilimanjaro"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Some structures along this body of water served as shelters for refugees from the Bar\nKokhba Revolt. The first known copy of The Community Rule was found here, along with\ncopies of known texts produced by the (20 pts) ",
        "Essenes. A famous discovery made near this\nbody of water centered on several (10 pts) ",
        "caves near Qumran. For ten points, name this body of water\nnear which a large collection of Hebrew writings was found in the 1940s and 1950s, this place’s namesake\n“Scrolls”."
      ],
      "answer": "Dead Sea"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An incident in this body of water’s Macondo Prospect led to a moratorium announced\nby Ken Salazar. A delta known as the Bird’s Foot extends into this body of water, whose\ncoast is home to many (20 pts) ",
        "bayous. Oil gushed into this body of water for 87 days in 2010\nafter the Deepwater Horizon explosion, and a (10 pts) ",
        "2005 hurricane that gained strength here\ndevastated New Orleans. For ten points, name this gulf of the Atlantic Ocean where Hurricane Katrina\nstruck the Mississippi River Delta."
      ],
      "answer": "Gulf of Mexico"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This agreement resolved the underlying dispute of Cresap’s War. David Rittenhouse and\nAndrew Ellicott finished mapping this agreement after Iroquois guides refused to cross into (20 pts) ",
        "Lenape territory. It includes a 12-mile arc around New Castle, outside of which lies a\n“wedge” once claimed by both (10 pts) ",
        "Delaware and Pennsylvania. This agreement is named for the\ntwo British surveyors who mapped it. For ten points, name this line geographically separating Maryland\nand Pennsylvania, which symbolically separated free Northern states from slave-owning Southern states."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Mason-Dixon line",
        "Mason-Dixon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) Writing under the name “Hercules,” Jesse Hawley put forth an idea for this\nobject, which was laid out by James Geddes and Benjamin Wright. The “Bucktails”\nwere annoyed with Governor (20 pts) ",
        "DeWitt Clinton over this object, which connected\nthe Mohawk and Hudson rivers and ran from (10 pts) ",
        "Albany to Buffalo. For ten points, name\nthis canal built in New York during the early 19th century."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Erie Canal",
        "Erie"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Project Seal attempted to use bombs to generate these events. They have low amplitude\nbut long (20 pts) ",
        "wavelength, which make them difficult to detect until they undergo shoaling\nin shallow areas. (10 pts) ",
        "Warnings about the oncoming of these events are issued from a center in Hawai’i.\nFor ten points, floods in Japanese coastal cities are often due to what kind of very large wave that is\ntypically caused by an earthquake?"
      ],
      "answer": "tsunami"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Edwin Lutyens designed a section of this city near the Lodhi Gardens that is home\nto hundreds of bungalows for public officials. This city’s (20 pts) ",
        "Raisina Hill is home to the\nRashtrapati Bhavan mansion and estate, formerly known as the Viceroy’s House. In 1911,\nthe British (10 pts) ",
        "Raj moved its government to this city, a more central site than the original, eastern\nCalcutta. For ten points, name this city, home to the National Capital Territory of India."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "New Delhi",
        "Delhi"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This state’s Fort Snelling was built near an early settlement at Mendota and several\nmiles downstream from the St. Anthony Falls. A body of water here was given a faux-Native\nAmerican name by Henry Schoolcraft, who combined the (20 pts) ",
        "Latin words for “truth” and\n“head.” The Treaty of 1818 gave this state’s territory an exclave north of the 49th Parallel,\non the other side of the (10 pts) ",
        "Lake of the Woods. The Northwest Angle is part of, for ten points, what\nMidwestern state where Lake Itasca is the source of the Mississippi River, and whose capital is St. Paul?"
      ],
      "answer": "Minnesota"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this present-day state, John Sevier led a government that petitioned Congress for\nstatehood in 1785. A “secret city” in this state was home to the K-25 and Y-12 plants, which\nenriched uranium for the (20 pts) ",
        "Manhattan Project. The self-proclaimed State of Franklin\nwas established in the eastern portion of this state, where the city of (10 pts) ",
        "Oak Ridge was built\nin 1942 west of Knoxville. For ten points, name this state that shares the Great Smoky Mountains with\nits eastern neighbor, North Carolina, and has its capital at Nashville."
      ],
      "answer": "Tennessee"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the far southwest corner of this sea, divers discovered the Antikythera analog\ncomputer. The Dodecanese islands lie in the extreme southeast of this sea. Chapter 20 of\nthe Book of Acts describes Paul sailing on the eastern shores of this body of water past (20 pts) ",
        "Ephesus, Miletus, and Samos. According to myth, this sea’s namesake threw himself into it\nwhen his son’s ship arrived from (10 pts) ",
        "Crete with black sails accidentally flying. For ten points, name\nthis offshoot of the Mediterranean Sea that separates Greece and Turkey."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Aegean Sea",
        "Aegean"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A kingdom in this region launched the Gihae Eastern Expedition to eradicate piracy on\na nearby island. The Silla kingdom ruled this location until its 935 annexation by the (20 pts) ",
        "Goryeo dynasty, which helped provide this location’s name. A phonetic alphabet native to\nthis region, hangul, was introduced by (10 pts) ",
        "Sejong the Great of the Joseon Dynasty, who sought an\nalliance with Ming China. For ten points, name this East Asian peninsula that has been divided between\ntwo countries since a 1950s war."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Korean Peninsula",
        "Korea"
      ]
    }
  ]
}